Guide to the Stephen Blank Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Stephen Blank papers
1916-1976
1942-1970
MS 1468
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.25
(3 boxes)
The papers consist of minutes, reports, clippings, and research notes compiled by Stephen Blank in his study of the Federation of British Industries and other organizations of British employers.
Blank, Stephen
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Stephen Blank, 1987 and 2008.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Stephen Blank Papers consist of minutes, reports, clippings, and research notes compiled by Blank in his study of the Federation of British Industry (FBI) and other organizations of British employers. The papers document the history of the FBI and the merger of the FBI, the National Association of British Manufacturers, and the British Employers Confederation to form the Confederation of British Industry in 1965. There are also papers on the National Economic Development Council.
Blank donated his papers to the Yale University Library, along with an extensive collection of printed books and pamphlets for the general collection, in 1987. The papers are aranged in four sections: Federation of British Industries; Confederation of British Industry; National Economic Development Council; and Reprints and notes relating to Blank's research on British industry during World War II.
The bulk of the material is in the Federation of British Industries section, which includes documents such as minutes, committee reports, and memoranda of the federation collected by Blank, as well as his extensive handwritten research notes. Blank's notes are scattered throughout the files as well as in folder 18. Files on the Economic Policy Committee of the FBI include a transcript of the 1956 weekend conference leading to a statement of economic problems facing Britain and proposed policies for their solution. Material in the Committee on Economic Programmes and Targets file concerns the Beaver Committee and its role in the formation of the National Economic Development Council.
The Confederation of British Industry section is composed of the minutes of the confederation from its beginning in 1965 until 1970, memoranda by the director-general, newsletters, and reports. The National Economic Development Council section includes background material and Blank's notes on the organization as well as copies of statements by two of the council's directors.
Biographical / Historical
Stephen Blank (born 1939) earned a BA degree, Dartmouth College, 1961, Certificate in Historical Studies, Cambridge University, 1963, and MA and Ph.D. degrees, Harvard University, 1966 and 1968. He joined the faculty of Pace University in 1981, was named Professor of International Business and Management at Pace's Lubin School of Business (1985), and served as Director of the Lubin Center for International Business Development, from 1998 to 2004. Blank is the author of Industry and Government in Britain: The Federation of British Industries in Politics, 1945-1965.
Employers' associations -- Great Britain; Great Britain -- Economic policy; Great Britain -- Industries; Blank, Stephen; Confederation of British Industry; Federation of British Industries; National Economic Development Council
- Inventory
  - Federation of British Industries
    - General, 1916-1965 (Box 1, Folder 1-7)
    - Committee on Economic Programmes and Targets, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Development Councils, 1945-1951 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Economic Policy Committee, 1948-1960 (Box 1, Folder 10 - 12)
    - European free trade area, 1956-1961 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Home Economic Policy Committee, 1947-1953, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
      General
      See also: Folders 10 - 12
    - Merger to form Confederation of British Industries, 1943-1963 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - National income policy, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Structure and operation, 1946-1964 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Notes, miscellaneous, 1947-1962 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Confederation of British Industry
    - Memoranda by the director-general, newsletters, reports, 1965-1970 (Box 2, Folder 19 - 20)
    - Minutes, 1965-1970 (Box 2, Folder 21 - 27)
  - National Economic Development Council
    - General, 1961-1968 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Fraser, T.C., 1963, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Shone, Sir Robert, 1963-1966, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Reprints and notes relating to Blank's research on British industry during World War II, 1940s-1999 (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
    - Government-business relations in Britain, 1940s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Articles, 1943-1973, 19999
      - British policy-making and administration, 1943-1973, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - British wages/incomes policy, 1955-1966 (Box 3, Folder 3)